我 的 父 親 母 親
本片改編自鮑十所著小說「紀念」
父親突然去世了
My father died suddenly.
我是昨天晚上知道的
I only found out last night.
村長給我打了一個長途電話
The mayor called to tell me.
當時我真不敢相信
I couldn't believe it.
我的家在山區  一個不大的村子
My hometown is in the mountains...
叫三合屯
a village called Sanhetun.
我很早就離開家鄉出來工作了
I left to work in the city.
因為忙  幾年都回不了一次家
I'm so busy I haven't been home in years.
父親是村裏的小學老師
My father was the village schoolteacher.
在當地教了一輩子書
He taught there all his life.
我是父母唯一的孩子
I am an only child.
也是村裏唯一念過大學的
The only one from our village who went to college.
我現在最擔心的就是母親  怕她一下子受不了
I am very worried about my mother.
師傅  進屋喝口水歇會兒吧
Come in and rest a while.
不了  我還要趕緊回去呢
I've got to get back.
那回去跟你們老總說  回頭我當面謝他
Thank your boss again for me.
- 不客氣    - 謝謝啊
- Thank you.    - Goodbye.
媽
Mother?
生子
Yusheng.
村長  夏大叔
Mayor, Uncle Xia.
在外頭看見車  才知道你回來了
I saw the car and knew you were back.
那進屋吧
Come in.
屋裏暖和
It's warmer inside.
你也坐  坐吧
Please. Sit down.
給你去個電話  說情況也沒說清楚
I couldn't tell you much over the phone.
這次你回來呀  給你說一說
Now you're here, I can explain everything.
咱村裏這個學校啊
It's the schoolhouse.
你爸是早就要求要翻蓋  多少年了吧
For many years your father has wanted to rebuild it,
因為村裏困難  也沒答應
but there were always reasons we couldn't.
現在你爸又張羅要翻蓋學校
He brought it up again recently,
村裏這回就決定要翻蓋學校
and the village agreed.
可是木料都預備夠了  還缺錢
We have the materials we need but not enough money.
沒錢他就急了
Your father's mind was set.
他著急啊  他就趕著出去借
He was determined to find the money.
關於你爸借錢  可跑了多少趟
He began traveling around, trying to borrow the money.
這兒  那兒  凡是他不錯的
He went all over the county.
有詞兒的人
If he thought there was a chance,
他都張羅去借去
he'd go after it.
結果呢  這趟回來
On the last trip, on his way home...
在路中就給趕上了風雪  特別大
he ran into a snowstorm, a big blizzard.
就給激了  激病了
He was stuck in the storm, and he got sick.
這兩天白毛風
He was too sick to be moved.
激病了
That made him more anxious.
激病了回來一看不行了
He was in bad shape when he got back,
這就送到縣城醫院經過了看
so we took him to the hospital.
這一看啊  是心臟病
They examined him, said he had a heart problem.
咱們你說老哥在這兒多少年
We've known your dad all these years.
不知道他有心臟病  結果呢  是心臟病
Who knew he had a heart condition?
治療了  看了不行
They tried treating him, but it was no use.
這就結果呢  你爸也就不頂了
He fought, but he didn't make it.
我爸在哪兒呢
Where is my father now?
現在在縣醫院呢  在太平房
At the provincial hospital, in the morgue.
這不就等著你回來
That's why we wanted you to return.
跟你商量
To tell you all this.
上次通電話的時候還挺好  咋整的呢
Last time I spoke with him, he seemed fine.
就是年紀大了  再趕上風雪
It was a bad storm.
人上歲數  再趕上這大雪天  大白毛風
At his age, it was too much for him.
這一激  受不了啦
It would have been
人是不頂了
hard on anyone.
我們村的意思呢  是打算明天待一天
The village wants to arrange a car
後天咱們用車給他接回來
to bring your father back.
- 已經三天了    - 在咱們村給他安葬就得了
- It's been three days.    - Bring him back here to bury him.
大概就這個意思
That's what we planned.
那就按村長的意思辦吧  我沒啥意見
That's fine. Go ahead.
沒啥意見  還有一個問題
But there is a problem.
這問題就是你媽不同意拿車拉
Your mother doesn't want to use a car.
她要求是抬回來
She wants your father to be carried back.
抬是啥意思啊
What do you mean?
抬就是  按老迷信說就是  再返回來走走老路
She wants the coffin brought back on foot...
回來看看這個老路  就是別忘這個老路吧
so your father won't forget his way home.
- 這是老一套迷信    - 那我媽是這麼想的嗎
- It's an old tradition, a superstition.    - I see.
她還想陪著也走回來跟著
And she wants to walk with us.
那就抬
So let's do it.
抬呢  咱們村裏也同意
We want to.
在這教了多少年學了  要說抬  也沒問題
He was our village teacher. Everyone respects him.
實際上咱們村子裏  現在是年輕人都走光了
But our young people have all left for the city.
都在外面做活
They've gone away to work.
盡剩些老的老小的小
Only old people and children are left.
村裏的意思是想用拖拉機
We thought of using a tractor.
半天也就拉回來了
We could make the trip in half a day.
這回讓你回來做做你媽的工作
You must help your mother decide.
行  大爺  你們別為難
I appreciate your concern.
這事兒我跟我媽說說  勸勸她
I will talk it over with her.
- 對    - 唉  我媽呢
- Good.    - Where is she?
你爸死了她就上那學校坐著
Probably at the schoolhouse.
一到學校就發呆坐著  誰勸也不行
She's there every day since he died.
- 誰勸也不回來    - 她這一坐就是半天
- She won't listen to anyone.    - She just sits there.
- 沒啥事兒吧    - 沒啥事兒
- Is she okay?    - I think so.
就怕她也
I am only afraid--
是不是以前那學校啊
The old schoolhouse?
就是以前的學校
Yes.
那我過去看看
I'll go to her.
- 媽    - 生兒
- Mother.    - Yusheng.
天這麼冷  咱們回家去吧
It's so cold. Let's go home, okay?
你爸不在了
Your father is dead.
走  咱們回家  媽
Let's go home.
再也看不著你爸了
You will never see him again.
媽  上炕暖和暖和吧
Get on the bed where it's warm.
生子  你跟我搬織布機去
Yusheng. Bring me my loom.
織布機  搬它幹啥  媽
What for?
我要織布
I want to weave something.
織啥布
Weave what?
我要給你爸織塊擋棺布
A cloth for your father's coffin.
媽  你看這樣行不行
Don't trouble yourself.
咱們別織了  我上供銷社給你買一塊
Why don't we go buy one instead?
買的我不要
I don't want to buy one.
織布機都幾十年了
That loom is so old.
早都壞了  再說現在誰還自己織布呢
It's been broken for years.
壞了  叫你夏大叔修修嘛
Why can't we fix it?
我看  媽
You need rest, Mother.
這兩天你這身體也是太累了
You must be so tired.
那我也得親手給他織一塊擋棺
I have to make this cloth.
我現在就給您買去  行嗎
Can't I just buy one?
買的我不要  我叫你搬你就搬
No, just bring me the loom.
咱們村子裏  根本就沒有織布機了
The only loom left in the village...
你媽呀  還留這麼一個
his this one of your mother's.
當寶貝似的留著
She's guarded it like a treasure.
看起來呀  你媽要織布  修的這個織布機要織布
Looks like she's determined to use it.
那就是要抬了
Just like the funeral procession.
抬的意思也就是過去那麼個老習慣
Carrying the dead is an old custom.
什麼過個山了
Over the mountains...
過個溝了  過個路口了
across the river, past the crossroads.
這就喊著點
And we shout at him along the way.
就喊點什麼呢  什麼意思呢
What do we say?
就是走這兒  叫他記住這個道兒
We tell him this is the road home.
大伙在這喊著點
Everyone yells at him,
叫他記住這個道兒
so that he remembers his way home.
就這麼個意思
It's an old tradition.
夏大叔  我想問問
Is it really so difficult
要是非抬不可的話  咱村裏確實有困難  真抬不了
to do as my mother wishes?
咱們村裏確實有困難
It is a problem, yes.
這個沒有勞力
We don't have the manpower.
勞力都出去了  加了就是老的老小的小了
All our young people have left.
抬回來  那都是文化大革命以前的事兒了
No one has followed this custom...
現在誰抬你  確實在沒有人
since the Cultural Revolution.
我真不想讓母親織這塊布
I don't want her to work like this...
可我不知道怎樣勸她
but I don't know how to stop her.
把父親抬回來
The funeral procession...
似乎是母親現在唯一的想法
seems all that matters to her now.
媽  聽老村長說  您想把爸抬回來
Mother, I know about your wishes for the funeral.
是的
Yes.
我是想  挺麻煩的  要不然就再想個辦法
Is there some other way to arrange it?
你別替他們操心麻煩
I know it won't be easy.
你看你爸到這村四十多年
But your father lived here for 40 years.
為這個學校  給他們培養出多少左一代右一代的學生
He taught many generations of kids.
起早睡晚的  心都操碎了
He worked very hard. Long, long hours.
咱們就這麼點事兒  他們給咱們講出這麼些困難
The town should give him something back.
那村長倒是沒有別的意思
The mayor agrees with you.
他就說了個困難
How about this?
我是覺得吧  媽  你說拿人抬回來
We can walk alongside...
和拖拉機拉回來  不是都一樣嗎
with the coffin pulled by a tractor.
不都是接我爸回來
We'd still be with him, right?
這個就不一樣
It's not the same.
怎麼也得找人去
I want your father carried back...
把你爸一塊兒接回來
by the men.
再不成  他們有困難  咱們想辦法
If they won't help...
咱們去人  一塊兒把你爸接回來
we'll get someone who will.
你今天晚上就別織了  行嗎
Please don't work anymore.
這塊布  我非得一定要把它織完了
I have to. I have to finish it.
你累好幾天了  你休息休息吧  行嗎
You are tired. Get some rest, okay?
你上你爸上課那屋睡覺吧
You sleep in your father's study.
我今天還非得把它織出來
I have to finish this.
這張照片  還是父親和母親結婚那年照的
This picture was taken the year my parents married.
父親原本不是我們三合屯的人
My father was not from the village.
他是後來才來的
He came here to teach.
當年父親和母親談戀愛的事兒
The story of my parents' courtship...
曾經轟動一時
is well-known in the village.
村裏人說來說去的  聽起來都像個故事
Practically everyone here has heard about it.
那年母親剛滿十八歲
My mother had just turned 18.
父親也只有二十歲
My father was 20.
聽母親說
My mother told me
是一輛馬車把父親拉到了三合屯
my father arrived by horse cart.
駕
Yah!
這就是來咱們三合屯教書的先生
This is our new teacher, Mr. Luo.
- 姓駱  叫駱長余    - 別叫先生  叫老師就行了
- His name is Luo, Luo Changyu.    - Just call me Luo.
是娣兒呀
Is that Di?
慌慌張張的幹啥呢
What's all the racket for?
沒幹啥
Nothing.
今兒一大早鬧鬧轟轟的  都說是去看先生  先生來了嗎
Has the teacher arrived?
來了
Yes.
這多好  咱們三合屯  總算也有了先生了
It's about time we got our own teacher.
那先生是啥樣啊
What does he look like?
是個小伙子
He's a young man.
小伙子  小伙子就當先生了
A young teacher?
這小伙子倒真能耐
He must be talented.
那他住哪兒呀
Where is he staying?
村政府吧
At the village council office.
村政府倒也行
That's good.
那東屋有鋪炕  吃飯呢
Where will he eat?
吃派飯  一家一天輪著吃
He'll eat with a different family each day.
那也該派到咱家
When it's our turn,
到時候啊  可得給先生吃飽嘍
we'll have to make a good meal.
娣兒  你在幹啥呢
What are you doing?
沒幹啥
Nothing.
看先生就看先生
Seeing a teacher
還換什麼新衣裳
has you changing clothes?
姥姥的眼睛那時候已經瞎了
My grandmother was already blind by then.
聽母親說  是姥爺死的時候
Mother says when Grandfather died...
姥姥天天哭  把眼睛給哭壞了
Grandmother cried until she went blind.
姥爺死後
After Grandfather died,
家裏就沒有其他人了  就母親陪著姥姥
there was only Mother to look after Grandmother.
姥姥一門心思
Grandmother's only wish
想給母親找個好婆家
was to find a good husband for Mother.
提親的人倒是很多
She had many proposals...
母親一個都沒看上
but my mother didn't like any of them.
父親已經來了
The schoolhouse was not yet built
村裏的學校還沒有蓋好
when my father arrived.
那幾天  村長正領著鄉親們趕著蓋
The mayor enlisted all the men's help.
照我們當地的習俗
According to our village custom...
新房蓋好的時候
a red cloth must be hung in a new building.
都要在樑上裹一塊紅布  圖個吉利
It's hung on the ceiling beam for good luck.
這塊布就叫紅
The cloth is called the lucky red banner.
通常是由
It must be woven
村裏最漂亮的姑娘來織
by the village's most beautiful maiden.
這次織紅的事兒  自然又落在了我母親的身上
This task, of course, fell to my mother.
也許是因為心裏有了父親的原因吧
Perhaps she was already a little in love...
這塊紅  母親織得格外仔細
because the cloth she made was especially fine.
當年村裏有兩口井
The village had two wells back then.
以前的井叫前井
The old well was called the "front well."
後來新打的那口井叫後井
The newer well was called the "back well."
後井近
The new well was nearer the village,
人們通常都在後井打水
so more people used that one.
自從父親來了以後
After my father arrived...
母親就改在前井打水了
Mother started to use the old well.
因為這樣會路過學校
She had to pass the schoolhouse to get to it.
照那時候的規矩
The village had another custom.
凡是蓋房這類大事兒
When putting up a new building,
家家戶戶都要往工地上送飯  給幹活兒的男人吃
each family prepared a dish for the workers' lunch.
這叫送公飯
Everyone contributed.
那幾天  母親盡挑好吃的做
Mother prepared all her best dishes,
她總希望父親能吃上她親手做的飯
hoping Father would eat what she made.
聽母親說  以前有挺多事兒  女人都不能上前
Back then when something was built...
比方說蓋房子  還有打井這種大事兒
women were not allowed to participate.
說怕沾上邪氣兒
Superstition said they would bring bad luck.
所以現在蓋學校
When they put up the school,
村裏的婦女們就只能離得遠遠的
the village women could only watch
在一邊看
from a distance.
大姐  今天你送的什麼飯呀
What did you make today?
饅頭和烙餅
Steamed bread.
招娣  你送的什麼飯
What about you, Di?
我送蔥油餅
I made onion cakes.
你送蔥油餅  我送苞米碴干飯
I brought rice steamed in lotus leaves.
苞米碴干飯可沒有蔥油餅好吃
Onion cakes are better.
你留什麼好吃的  晚上偷著給你男人吃呢
Did you save some for your boyfriend?
你胡說
Shut up!
你沒看見嗎
Look at them.
他們都是亂吃
They just pick up the first dish they see.
誰也不知道誰吃的誰家的
They don't know who made what.
我送的包子不知道誰吃了
I don't know who's eating mine.
讓你男人吃了
Must be your husband!
放著吧
Put them here.
招娣  你把紅給送來了
You're already done with the banner?
我還正要到你家去取呢
I was going to come get it from you.
給我  給我啊
Give it to me.
行  行  給你
Okay.
還省得我給你去送呢
You'll save me a further trip.
招娣  你這紅織得可真好
This is a beautiful banner.
過兩天一上梁  學校蓋好了  就能上課了
The school is almost finished.
先生說  第一天上語文
Chinese study will be the first lesson.
那先生這兩天吃得好不好
Is the teacher happy with the food?
好啊
Yes.
他也跟著吃公飯
Does he eat what we make?
是啊
Yes.
那他也搶著吃
He eats together with you?
哪能吶  人家是城裏來的文化人
No. He's a city gentleman.
不能和咱們一塊搶著吃
It's not proper for him to eat with us.
那他咋吃的
So how does it work?
每次都是緊著先生端頭一份兒
We give him first pick of the dishes.
人生在世  念
"In life--" Follow me.
人生在世
"In life--"
要有志氣  念
"You must make goals."
要有志氣
好  咱們再讀第二遍
Start from the beginning.
讀書識字  多長見識  念
"One must learn to write." Follow me.
讀書識字  多長見識
"One must learn to write."
能寫會算  是件好事  念
"One must learn arithmetic."
能寫會算  是件好事
大事小情  提筆就記  念
"Keep a journal faithfully."
大事小情  提筆就記
知今知古  知天知地  念
"Know the present, know the past."
知今知古  知天知地
小時候聽母親說起過
When I was young, my mother told me
父親唸書的聲音特別好聽
my father had a beautiful voice.
母親不識字
My mother never learned to write,
有的課文她也聽不懂
was never interested in school.
但是她覺得父親的聲音是天底下最好聽的聲音
But she couldn't resist the sound of my father's voice.
從這一天開始  母親就天天去聽
She went by the school every day after that.
後來村裏人習慣了  就沒人再去聽了
For most, the novelty of the new school wore off after a while...
可是母親還是去聽
but not for my mother.
她一聽就聽了四十多年
For 40 years, she came to listen...
這已經成了她生活中的一部分
and it became part of her life.
長幼尊卑  敬重有序  念
"Know respect for your elders."
長幼尊卑  敬重有序
母親聽說每天放學的時候
Each day after school...
父親都要送幾個路遠的孩子回家
my father walked some of his students home.
她就動了心思  想在那條路上碰見父親
Knowing this, my mother waited along the way.
太陽光  金亮亮  雄雞唱三唱
♪ The birds sing with the beautiful sun ♪
花兒醒來了  鳥兒忙梳妝
♪ Their songs wake the beautiful flowers ♪
嘿
Hey!
她是誰呀
Who is she?
她是老田家的招娣
That's Zhao Di.
那她是咱三合屯的人嗎
Is she from Sanhetun?
住在後街那兒
Yes.
招娣姐  我們老師問你呢
Di, the teacher is asking about you!
先生  挑水去
You need water?
唉
Yes.
來來來  我幫你挑
Let me get it for you.
不用  我自己來
No, that's okay.
我來我來
Let me do it.
不  不  不  沒事兒  沒事兒
I can do it. Thanks.
你客氣什麼嘛  這活兒我們都幹慣了
No, let me. Let me help you!
您是教書的  您怎麼能幹這活呢
You're the teacher. You shouldn't bother.
我來  我來
Let me do it.
不用  我自己來就行
No, no.
不行  不行
Come on.
我行
Let me do it.
招娣  你咋跑前井打水來啦
Di, you're fetching water as well?
明天該輪到我家吃飯了
Tomorrow it's our turn to have you over.
我知道
I know.
父親對我說過
My father told me...
他第一次到母親家吃派飯的時候
the first time he went to my mother's house,
母親站在門口迎他
she stood in the doorway.
他記得母親扶著門框  站在門口的樣子
Leaning against the door frame...
就像一幅畫
she looked like a figure in a painting...
他說很多年他都忘不了這幅畫
an image he would never forget.
娣兒  是先生來了吧
Is the teacher here?
來了
Yes.
我就說嘛  這腳步聲這麼重
Your heavy footsteps gave you away.
快到屋裏來  我看看
Come in. Come here.
我娘的眼睛壞了
My mother's eyesight is not good.
噢
Oh.
這先生這麼高啊
This teacher is very tall.
坐下  坐下
Sit down.
上炕吧
Please!
家裏多少年沒有男人吃飯了
Can't think when we last had a man home for dinner.
聽聽  吃得真香啊
The food must taste good to you.
嚼得多有勁啊
You sound like you're enjoying it.
先生來咱們三合屯有一個月了吧
How long have you been here?
一個多月了
About a month.
還待得慣嗎
Have you gotten used to it?
待得慣
It's okay.
待得慣就好
That's good.
先生家在縣上住
You're from the city?
縣上東關
Yes, from East Gate.
那咋來三合屯呢
How did you choose Sanhetun?
學校畢業  在家沒事兒
After graduation, I couldn't find work.
在縣上亂逛  看見敲鑼打鼓的  喊人報名
One day in the street, a man was signing people up.
也不知道幹啥的  沒仔細問  我就報了一個
I didn't know what for, but I signed up anyway.
這不就來了
And I ended up here.
那不後悔
Do you regret it?
不後悔
No.
為啥
Why?
我喜歡
I like it here.
先生還沒成家
Are you married?
沒呢
No.
也沒定親
Are you engaged?
沒呢
No.
你別管  讓招娣收拾  坐著  歇會兒
Di will do it. Sit for a while.
你認得我家的碗嗎
Do you remember this bowl?
就這青花的
This design?
我不認得
No, I don't remember.
你吃沒吃公飯
Did you eat the food brought to the site?
吃了
Yes.
這可真是瞎了招娣的一片心了
Looks like Di's hard work was wasted.
別看都不說  我可都知道  蓋學堂  吃公飯
You know when you were building the school,
她是調著樣兒做好的
she made all her best dishes.
回回都拿這青花碗送過去
She always used that bowl,
就指盼著先生能吃上一口
hoping you would choose her dish.
連我都不讓動上一筷子
Even I wasn't allowed to help.
噢  吃公飯啊  這碗我還真使過
I remember now.
你使過
You do?
我說嘛  有點眼熟  使過
The bowl and your cooking are familiar.
碗裏的飯你也吃了
So you ate from it before?
吃了
Yes.
你說  都吃啥了
You did? What did you eat?
呃
Uh...
我跟你說  我頭一天送的是蔥花油餅
On the first day, I made onion cakes.
第二天  送的是小米飯  蔥花炒雞蛋
On the second, scrambled eggs and onions on rice.
第三天  送的是蘑菇餡蒸餃
On the third day, mushroom dumplings.
真可惜啦  這麼好吃的三頓飯
What a shame. Three delicious meals.
蘑菇餡蒸餃我最愛吃了
And I love mushroom dumplings.
那你後晌來  我給你做
I'll make you some this afternoon.
太麻煩了
That is too much to ask.
不麻煩
No.
這剛吃了前晌
You've hardly finished lunch,
就惦著後晌了
and you're planning the next meal.
招娣  送先生走  先生還忙著呢
Di, show the teacher out. He must be very busy.
對  我該走了
Yes, I should go.
你穿那件紅衣裳真好看
That red jacket of yours is pretty on you.
來的頭一天我就看見了
I remember it from the day I arrived.
- 後晌你一定要來吃餃子    - 唉
- Don't forget to come back for dumplings.    - Okay.
我說  就別包那餃子了
You shouldn't make the dumplings.
為啥不包
Why not?
免得後悔
You may regret it.
我悔啥
Why?
悔啥你自己知道
You don't understand.
那先生  好是好
This teacher is a nice man,
他跟咱不是一路人  這事兒不成
but he's out of our class.
有啥成不成的  不就吃頓餃子嗎
What are you talking about? It's only dumplings.
你別給我裝糊塗
Don't play dumb.
我把話給你撂下
I'm just being honest.
你就死了這心吧
You'd best forget about him.
我不回去就是不回去
I will not go back!
你別無選擇
You've got no choice!
我來跟你說一聲  我要走了
I came to say goodbye.
走  走哪兒啊
Where are you going?
我回縣裏面
Back to the city.
啥事兒這麼急
What's happened?
沒啥事兒
Nothing.
我在井台上看到他跟你吵架了
I saw you argue with someone.
是他叫你回去的
Was that what it was about?
他是誰呀  你回去幹啥
Who was he? Why do you have to go back?
真沒啥事兒
It's no big deal.
他們是有事兒問我  問完就完了唄
They just want to ask me some questions. That's all.
那在這兒不能問
Can't they ask you questions here?
他做不了主
He says it's not up to him.
那你還回來嗎
Will you come back?
回來  我一定回來  學生們等我上課呢
Of course. I have classes to teach.
那你啥時候回來
When will you be back?
最晚  臘月初八我一定回來
By the 27th at the latest.
臘月初九  學生放假
On the 28th, the school holiday starts.
我得在放假前回來
I have to be back before that.
進屋吃餃子吧
Come in and eat something.
餃子恐怕吃不了了
I can't.
還有事兒呢  你和你娘就別等了
I have things to do before I go.
真還有事兒呢  他等著我呢
I really do. That man is waiting for me.
那你招呼他一塊兒來吃吧
Tell him to come too.
啥要緊事兒也得先吃飯吶
You have to eat in any case.
行  我來吃
Okay, I'll be back.
那我等著你
I'll wait for you.
這個是我給你買的
This is for you.
配你那件紅衣裳  好看
To go with your red jacket.
那我等著你啊
I'll be waiting.
唉
Okay.
到底咋回事兒啊  這不正上課著嗎
What is going on? No more class?
說是要讓他當個右派
He's in some political trouble.
啥派
Political trouble?
我也整不明白  反正沒啥大事兒
I don't understand it either. But maybe it's nothing.
說不定過兩天就回來了
Said he might be back in a day or two.
先生走了
The teacher's left.
先生走了嗎
The teacher's left?
走了
Yes.
他走了
Just left?
剛剛村長他們把他送走
Just left with the mayor.
母親一連好幾天早出晚歸
My mother retraced her steps every day...
她把那幾十里山路都跑遍了
searching back and forth.
她想找到父親留給她的那支髮夾
She had to find the clip my father had given her.
修碗  修盆
Pottery repairs!
鋦碗的
鋦碗的  進來
Please come in.
我是照釘收錢的
I charge for the nails I use.
這比買一個新碗可貴多了
This will cost you more than buying a new bowl.
該多少錢給多少錢  分文不短你的
Just tell me how much, and I'll pay you.
是祖上傳下來的嗎
Is it a family heirloom?
倒也不是
No.
那就是有人使過
It belonged to someone special?
算你說對了  有人使過
You could say that.
誰使過
Who?
不瞞你說  我這是替閨女鋦的
It's for my daughter.
使碗的人走了  把閨女的心也帶走了
The man who used it left
把這碗鋦好了  也給閨女留個念
and took my daughter's heart with him.
我給你把它鋦得滴水不漏
I've put it back together again.
保準給你閨女一個好念想
I hope she'll be happy.
修碗  修盆
Pottery repairs!
娣兒  你幹啥呢
Di, what are you doing?
沒幹啥  我舀口水喝
Nothing. Just getting a drink of water.
一八得八
1 times 8 equals 8.
一九得九
1 times 9 equals 9.
二二得四
2 times 2 equals 4.
二三得六
2 times 3 equals 6.
二四得八
2 times 4 equals 8.
二五一十
2 times 5 equals 10.
二六一十二
2 times 6 equals 12.
二七一十四
2 times 7 equals 14.
二八一十六
2 times 8 equals 16.
二九一十八
2 times 9 equals 18.
好
Good.
三三得九
3 times 3 equals 9.
三四一十二
3 times 4 equals 12.
三五一十五
3 times 5 equals 15.
三六一十八
3 times 6 equals 18.
三七二十一
3 times 7 equals 21.
三八二十四
3 times 8 equals 24.
三九二十七
3 times 9 equals 27.
父親對母親說過
My father told my mother
他給學生上課的時候
when he was teaching the kids,
一抬眼就能看見樑上那塊紅
he could always look up and see the red banner.
一看見那紅
When he saw that banner
就想起母親穿紅棉襖的樣子
it reminded him of Mother and her red jacket.
後來村長說過好幾次
The mayor kept insisting
要給教室吊個頂棚
that the ceiling needed proper insulation,
都被父親謝絕了
but my father never let him.
所以我們村的這個小學校  幾十年來就一直沒有頂棚
That's why the school ceiling was never completed.
那天母親在教室裏一直坐到很晚
Mother sat in the classroom for hours that day.
教室門開著  被村長看見了
The door was open, and the mayor saw her there.
村長這才明白了母親的心思
He understood what that meant.
村長知道了
Once he knew,
村裏人很快也都知道了
the news got around the village, quickly.
在當年
Back then, arranged matches were the rule.
自由戀愛還是一件很新鮮的事兒
The freedom of falling in love was unfamiliar.
母親給三合屯開了個頭
This was a first for our village.
到了父親答應回來的日子
On the day my father promised to return...
母親一大早就站在那條路上等
my mother was waiting from first light.
她記著父親說過的那句話
She remembered his promise:
臘月初八一定回來
that he would return on the 27th.
因為臘月初九學校就放假了
School vacation began on the 28th.
父親得在放假前趕回來
He had to be back before that.
看這身寒氣  幹啥去了  一天不著家
It's so cold out. Where have you been?
快上炕躺會兒
Gone all day. Get warm on the bed.
這麼燙  娣兒  你病了
You're burning up!
我知道你昨天迎先生去了
I know you went to wait for the teacher.
村裏的人都說  先生犯了錯誤  回不來了
Everyone says he's in trouble and won't be back.
你就別操這份心了
You've got to let go.
我到縣上找他去
I'm going to the city to find him.
你瘋了  你還病著呢  你上縣上咋找
Are you crazy?! You're ill!
娣兒  你回來  回來
Di! Come back!
那天母親沒走到縣城
My mother didn't make it to the city.
卻暈倒在半路上
She fainted by the road.
有過路人看見  給村裏捎了信兒
Someone saw her, and they got word to the mayor.
村長和夏大叔他們套上馬車  連夜把母親拉了回來
The mayor and my uncle brought her home on a cart.
我記得村長後來跟我說過一次
The mayor said that day,
說那天母親的兩手冰涼冰涼的
my mother's hands were like ice.
在馬車上
While on the cart,
他用皮襖暖了一路
they wrapped her in a heavy blanket,
都沒暖過來
but they couldn't get her hands warm.
不要緊  凍著了
I don't think it's too serious.
虛火上升  氣血淤滯  歇兩天就好了
It's a bad chill, but she is strong.
村長  你說說  這先生到底還能不能回來
Mayor, is the teacher coming back?
這城裏人的事兒  我也整不清楚
I don't know the answer.
照理說  他也該早回來了
He should have been back by now.
你們有誰方便啊  就給先生捎個信
Maybe someone can write to him.
他不回來  招娣咋辦  我也攔不住她呀
I don't know how to help her...
就讓先生回來呀  看上她一眼也好啊
if he doesn't come back.
春天來了
"Spring is here."
春風吹化了冰雪
"It melts the snow."
吹綠了草地
"The grass turns green."
農民在種莊稼
"The farmers sow."
牛在耕田
"The ox plow the field."
大雁回來了
"The wild geese return."
青蛙結束了冬眠
"The frogs begin to hop."
娣兒  你醒了
Di, you're awake.
你都睡了兩天了
You've been sleeping for two days.
你還不知道呢
Di, the teacher is back.
先生回來了
The teacher is back.
先生昨晚就回來了
He came back yesterday.
一回來就上咱們家來了
He came straight here.
就在這兒守了你半宿
He sat with you for a long time.
娣兒  這下可好了  先生回來了
Isn't it good news?
他這是為你回來的呀
He came back for you.
充滿勃勃的生機
"Full of energy."
我們的心情也跟萬物一樣
"Our spirit comes alive."
充滿新的希望
"It carries our wishes."
充滿新的理想
"Full of hope."
春天來了
"Spring is here."
春風吹化了冰雪
"It melts the snow."
吹綠了草地
"The grass turns green."
農民在種莊稼
"The farmers sow."
牛在耕田
"The ox plow the field."
大雁飛來了
"The wild geese return."
青蛙結束了冬眠
"The frogs begin to hop."
小燕子在欣喜地喳喳叫
"Swallows start to sing."
春天是播種的季節
"Spring is the season to sow."
萬物都在生長
"All starts to grow again."
充滿勃勃的生機
"The world is full of life again."
駱先生
Mr. Luo!
駱先生  招娣來看你了
Mr. Luo, Di is here to see you!
先生  先生
Sir!
招娣來了
Di is here!
天黑前  剛剛回來的父親就又被叫走了
That evening, my father had to leave again.
因為他是偷著跑回來的
When he heard about my mother, he left the city...
他是聽說了母親的情況後
without permission.
實在忍不住
He couldn't stand it any longer,
就私自跑回來了
so he sneaked back.
由於父親的這次行為
For this disobedience,
使他和母親最後見面的日子又推遲了好幾年
my parents were kept apart for another two years.
後來  我聽鄉親們說
Someone told me,
當父親真正和母親相聚的那一天到來時
that on the day my father finally returned,
母親又特意穿上了那件
my mother put on her red jacket,
父親喜愛的紅棉襖
my father's favorite,
站在路邊等著父親
and stood by the road to wait for him.
從那天起  父親就再沒離開過母親一步
From that day on, my father never left my mother again.
這就是父親和母親的故事
This is the story of my father and my mother.
他們相識  相愛的過程  都和這條路有關
This road is part of their love story...
這是我們村通往縣城的一條普通的山路
this road that leads from the city to our village.
也許就因為母親曾經那麼殷切
Maybe because of the hope it held for her
那麼長久地在這條路上等待過父親
as she waited for my father to return,
所以她還想陪著父親  再從這條路上走回來
she wants to walk this way with him one last time.
村長
Mr. Mayor?
誰呀
Who is it?
我  生子
It's me, Yusheng.
- 生子  有事兒嗎    - 有事兒
- You need to see me?    - Yes.
有事兒快進屋說  來  天挺冷的
Come in, come in. It's cold out there.
有什麼事兒啊
How can I help you?
我媽的心思啊  我想明白了
I've thought it through.
咱們還是抬吧
I want to do as my mother wishes.
你也要抬
To carry him back?
可是咱們村還有點困難
It's still a problem, though.
不就是人手不夠嗎
The problem is not enough men, right?
你看這樣行不行  村長
How about this:
咱們到鄰村雇點人來
We'll hire men from the next village.
僱人  鄰村倒是好雇
That's a good idea.
現在就這錢
But how do we pay them?
那沒關係  您幫我算算得多少人
Just tell me how many men we need.
人嘛  要是近點  有十幾多個人就夠
For a short distance, only 10,
因為咱們這兒離縣城太遠
but this is a long trip.
這個你必須得十六個人的杠子
I think we need about 16.
得兩班  兩班就得三十二個
We will need two shifts. That's 32 men.
三十二個呢  再有幾個閒人  拿凳子放在路中
And we'll need others to carry chairs,
有的人累了  可以擱上歇歇
so people can rest along the way.
這總共得個三十五六個人吧
That comes to about 35, 36 men.
那一個人得多少錢呢
How much per person?
一個人  現在咱就給他一百塊錢
One hundred yuan each should do.
就可以了
That will do.
三十五六個人
Thirty-five, 36 people.
那你給算算總共得多少錢
How much in total?
人嘛  三十五六個人  三千五六百塊錢
That's 3500 or 3600 yuan.
下來呀  有抽煙的  咱們還要給他買點煙
We need to buy cigarettes.
有喝酒的  這酒我也得買點  因為天太冷
And wine too, gotta ward off the cold.
要有點什麼事兒  都得用點錢
We'll also want a little extra for emergency use.
可能有四千多塊錢  就差不多了
Altogether, around 4000 yuan.
村長  這是五千塊錢  夠不夠
Here's 5000 yuan. Is that enough?
足夠了  用不了
It's more than enough.
老嫂子  去看看駱先生吧
Mrs. Luo, come and see Mr. Luo.
去看的時候可別哭
Please don't cry.
別讓眼淚掉在駱先生身上  不好的
Don't let tears fall on him.
駱先生  咱們現在回村了  要走好
Mr. Luo, we are going back to the village.
那天抬棺來了一百多個人
That day over 100 people came to the ceremony.
聽村長說  他們都是父親的學生
The mayor told me they were my father's students.
他們知道了這件事情  就都趕來了
They heard about his death, and they all came back.
有很多人都是從外地趕回來的
Many came from other towns.
也有從市裏坐著小車來的
Some drove from the city.
村長說  最遠的有從廣州趕過來的
The mayor said some came from as far as Guangzhou.
還有幾個人被風雪誤在了半路上
Some tried, but didn't make it in time,
沒有來得及
because of the snowstorm.
來得人大部分我都不認識
I didn't recognize many of them.
有的人比我大得多
Many were older than me.
我不知道他們都是父親哪一年的學生
I don't know when my father taught them.
也不知道該怎樣稱呼他們
I didn't know how to address them.
村長說
Anyway, as the mayor said,
反正都是駱先生的學生嘛
they are all my father's students.
生子  這些錢還給你吧
Take this money back.
咋能都不要呢  不是說好了的嗎
Why? Didn't you pay the men?
來的人都不要  就連拿錢雇的人也不要
They won't take it, not even the ones we hired.
就一分錢也不要
No one wants the money.
你還是收起來吧
Take it back.
按著母親的意思
At my mother's request,
父親就安葬在前井旁邊
my father was buried next to the old well.
村裏有了自來水  井就荒了
The village has running water now, so no one needs a well.
早就沒人再挑水了
No one draws water from it now.
母親說  在這兒
My mother says from this hill,
父親可以天天看見學校
my father can look down on the school.
母親還說  將來她也要跟父親埋在一起
She asks to be buried next to him when the time comes.
辦完父親的後事
After my father's funeral,
村長特意來說起了蓋學校的事兒
the mayor came to talk about rebuilding the school.
他說縣裏撥了款
The city has granted funds,
村裏家家戶戶也都捐了錢
and the village families have donated money.
說鄉親們無論如何也要完成父親的心願
He says we must fulfill my father's wishes.
生子  你帶回來的錢呢  給媽吧
Your money, give it to me.
村長  你看  這些錢都是我這幾十年積攢的
Mayor, we've saved over the years.
你把它收起來蓋學校吧
Take it to rebuild the school.
這咋好意思呢  你說  長余不在了
I can't take it.
這錢你一定得收下
With my husband gone, you have to take it.
那好  那我把這些錢先拿上
All right, I'll take it then.
咱們村  你們母子倆算第一份
You are the first, but surely not the last, to help.
明天我就要走了
I am leaving tomorrow.
母親讓我陪她再去一趟學校
Mother has asked me to go to the schoolhouse one last time.
母親說  等下次我再回來時
My mother says the next time I come back,
這所小學校就看不到了
the school we know will be gone.
生子  你看這學校都幾十年了
Your father helped build this school.
你爸就在這學校教書
He taught here so many years.
在這裏比在家待得時間還長
Spent as much time here as at home.
長余  你都聽到了嗎
Changyu, can you hear me?
村長說了  要蓋新學校
The mayor will rebuild the school.
按你的心願去蓋  蓋一個高大  漂漂亮亮的
They'll build a tall
一個好學校
and wonderful school...
為了完成你的心願  按你的意思去蓋
just as you wished.
明年開春就動工了
They will start building next spring.
這回你放心了吧
You won't have to worry anymore.
新學校蓋好了
When the school is completed,
我親手織一塊紅掛上去
I will hang a lucky red banner there.
你就放心吧
You can rest easy now.
你看看你爸  實心實意
You know, your father was a sincere man.
整天跟我說  想叫你教書
He always wanted you to become a teacher,
接他的班
to take over for him.
把你送到師範學校念了
You went to the teachers' college,
一天書你也沒教上
but you never taught a day of class.
哪怕你上一天課  教一天書
If you could teach for one day,
也是你爸爸這一片心都沒有實現了
I think it would make him happy.
你就幹別的工作去了
Then you can go back to your life.
你看  學校連上課的人都沒有了
Look, there's no teacher now.
聽不到孩子們唸書的聲音了
No sound of children reciting their lessons.
聽村長說  過兩天縣上可能還會派個新老師來
The mayor said a new teacher was on the way.
新老師來
Not many teachers,
再上課也沒有你爸爸聲音好聽啊  特別的響亮
would sound as good as your father.
四十多年我都沒聽夠
After 40 years, I still love that voice.
好聽呀  你爸讀書
I can still hear it.
媽  我考慮好了
Mother, I've been thinking.
這次你跟我回城裏  咱們一塊兒住
Why don't you come to the city with me?
我不去
No, thank you.
有你爸在這兒  哪兒我也不去
I won't leave your father.
把你自己留在這兒  讓我咋放心呢
How can I leave you here alone?
別為我擔心
Don't worry about me.
我自己會照顧我自己的
I can take care of myself.
你在城裏工作都好吧
Are you doing all right in the city?
好  媽
Yes.
特別好  你放心吧
Don't worry about me.
有女朋友嗎
Do you have a girlfriend?
到時候再說吧
Let's not talk about it.
你看  你都那麼大歲數了
You're not young anymore.
別挑剔了啊
Don't be so picky.
你聽媽告訴你
Listen to me.
有合適的  自己找一個
Find yourself a nice girl
找一個領回來  讓媽看看
and bring her home to meet me.
可是  你爸不在了
Your father's gone.
你爸呀  就為你這事擔心
He used to worry about you.
兒女大了  拴不住了
Our children must leave home.
離爹娘遠了  就看不到了
We can't keep you here forever.
做父母的
As parents...
兒女出了門  父母都擔心吶  你看
we let you go, but we never stopped worrying.
你爸  一直
Your father...
都掛念你  記著你
...missed you so.
- 別哭了  媽    - 你看他
- Please don't cry.    - Your father...
你老哭老哭  你看你這身體都壞了
Mother, please don't cry.
你看他去了  把咱們母子留下  孤孤單單的
With your father gone, it's hard not to feel lonely.
好了
I know.
你呀
You...
在外面好好工作啊
...must work hard and make a good life.
能寫會算  是件好事  念
"One must learn to read and write."
能寫會算  是件好事
大事小情  提筆就記  念
"Keep a journal faithfully."
大事小情  提筆就記
知今知古  知天知地  念
"Know the present, know the past."
知今知古  知天知地
春夏秋冬  一年四季  念
"Spring, summer, fall, winter. Four seasons in a year."
春夏秋冬  一年四季
東西南北  四方天地  念
"East, West, South, North."
東西南北  四方天地
風霜雪雨  事事在意  念
"In everything there is a purpose."
風霜雪雨  事事在意
我一大早就讓村長把學生們集合起來
I gathered the students early that morning.
我說我要給學生們上一節課
I told them I would teach them for one day.
村長問我為什麼
The mayor asked me why.
我說我是為了母親  也為了父親
I said it was for my mother and for my father too.
我就站在父親常站的那個地方
I stood in my father's place,
父親在這兒站了一輩子
where he stood for so many years.
我想  此時此刻  父親一定能聽見
I felt sure he could hear my voice,
我和孩子們唸書的聲音吧
and those of the students.
我念的就是當年父親在開學第一天念的那篇課文
The book I am using is the same one he used that first day.
其實這不是正式的課文
It is not a textbook.
這是父親自己編的一段識字歌兒
It is a book he wrote himself.
能寫會算  是件好事
"One must learn to read and write."
大事小情  提筆就記
"Keep a journal faithfully."
知今知古  知天知地
"Know the present, know the past."
春夏秋冬  一年四季
"Spring, summer, fall, winter. Four seasons in a year."
東西南北  四方天地
"East, West, South, North."
風霜雪雨  事事在意
"In everything there is a purpose."
長幼尊卑  敬重有序
"Know respect for your elders."
人生在世  要有秩序
"In life, you must make goals."
劇 終
THE END